A Guide to the Nevena Kechedzhieva Architectural Drawings 1971-1989
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Nevena Kechedzhieva Architectural Drawings 1971-1989
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2000-009
1 flat box, 1 tube box, 2 large oversized folders; 1.8 cu. ft.
Architect Nevena Kechedzhieva worked for the Bulgarian State Design Organization until 1984, and now designs for private clients. The collection contains her designs for residential and commercial projects in Bulgaria, Nigeria and Yemen from 1971 to 1989.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The creator donated the Nevena Kechedzhieva material to the International Archive of Woman in Architecture via Milka Bliznakov in the summer of 1998. Additional drawings were acquired from the donor the same way in early 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
Nevena Stoianova Kechedzhieva was born in 1927 in Sofia, Bulgaria. She studied architecture at Sofia Polytechnic, graduating in 1951. Thereafter, she worked for the State Design Organization, "Glavproekt," until her retirement in 1984. In the late 1970s Kechedzhieva was sent to work in Cuba. She worked in Nigeria, the People's Republic of Yemen (Aden) and Mozambique in the early 1980s. Kechedzhieva is also an accomplished interior designer. Since her retirement, she has continued to design for private clients.
Scope and Content
The bulk of this collection consists of architectural drawings created by Nevena Kechedzhieva from 1971 to 1989. It includes residential projects in Bulgaria and commercial projects in Nigeria, Yemen and Bulgaria. Undated sketches of concept plans and elevations for an unidentified multi-storey building are available. A wall unit sketch and her curriculum vitae are also included. Most of the information on the drawings is written in Bulgarian. Translated "Sheet Identification" information for the drawings is included in the collection.
Arrangement
The drawings are grouped by project and stored by size. The smaller sketches and the translated "Sheet Identification" information for most of the drawings are stored in the flat box. Oversize drawings for the Sunny Coast Resort in Bulgaria are stored rolled. The rest of the drawings are stored in oversize folders.
In order to provide translation information for the Bulgarian on each sheet, all the drawings stored in oversized folders have a pencil notation on the left of the title block along the bottom edge that included the initials "IAWA", a letter for that set of project drawings, and the sheet number. The corresponding translation for each drawing is stored in the flat box. For example, more information about the "Attached Houses for Three Families" in Bulgaria in folder one, marked IAWA D1 to IAWA D8, can be found by looking at the translation sheet under that code.
Contents List
- Curriculum vitae (Box-folder 1-1)
- Translations for drawings in oversize folder 1 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Translations for drawings in oversize folder 2 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Unidentified multi-storey project
  - Plan, sketches (10 sheets) (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Longitudinal elevation (3 sheets) (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Side elevation (4 sheets) (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Furniture design for a wall unit, sketch (1 sheet) (Box-folder 1-7)
- Sunny Coast Resort, Bulgaria 1971-1974 (13 sheets) (Box 2)
- Four projects, 1980-1987 (Oversize 1)
  - Hospital with 200 beds, Nigeria, 1980
  - Motels and bungalows, Gold Moore, Yemen, 1980-1982
  - Gas station with shops outside Sofia, Bulgaria, 1980s
  - Attached houses for three families (Penka Manolova, Manol Guimon, and Margarita Peltekova) in Sozopol, Bulgaria 1986-1987
- House for Spasen Marinov in Slivnitsa, Bulgaria, 1989-1989 (Oversize 2)